Now, we're used to seeing this kind of
thing out of the payroll reports, but I
don't think anyone was expecting this.
There were red flags all over the May
data coming from all sides, not the
least of which is the context behind
all of these big problems in the
numbers. Dollar Tree, for example, when
Dollar Tree says that its consumers, its
customers can no longer afford to buy
food from dollar stores, you know you've
got big problems. Gas prices are up,
everyone knows that because consumers
are paying more at the pump. They've
been outspoken in how much this has
forced them to cut back, and that's what
Dollar Tree's really saying, the
sacrifice is real. Now, thankfully, for
most Americans, they only have to trade
down a vacation, cancel a trip, maybe
give up some nights out. So, the last
thing you would ever expect to see is a
sudden burst of hiring in exactly that
part of the economy which is most
vulnerable to the pullback in
discretionary spending. And again,
Dollar Tree is saying the pullback is
very real. But that's just what the BLS
did in the payroll report where get
this, leisure and hospitality jobs just
soared by the most in over 3 years. Even
worse, this accounted for way more than
half of the private sector job gains
during the energy shock. And that's only
just the beginning from the dollar
stores to the BLS doing it this same
thing it always does. Yes, we've seen
this before, but this really does take
the cake, especially
right now.
So, Steve, we get this all the time.
We're used to the establishment server
the payroll number coming in way above
expectations, and then it gets revised
down later on. But this one, this one
really takes the cake. This one is kind
of out there as a exceptional extreme
outlier.
>> Yeah, Jeff, this morning when I pulled
it up, I was like, what is this? This is
ridiculous. I mean, where did they get
this number from? And then of course,
you see total leisure and hospitality,
you see government jobs, you see a lot
of part-time. Everything felt part-time
to me, and And just didn't make any
sense because you know you talk about
you know the income you know data
showing a recession in October. We can
look at real personal disposal income
went negative back in January. So it's
like all of a sudden we know people just
don't have that much money to spend and
yet all of a sudden the government's
like look at all these jobs created
which would tell you that people must be
out spending or the businesses had the
perception that people were going to go
out and spend and yet none of the
underlying data confirms that. You know
I love to look at weekly hours because
you know one of my base cases is that if
indeed as a business owner things were
booming the first thing I'm not going to
do is go out and hire someone. I'm going
to go to one of my employees who clearly
may be struggling financially and say
hey how would you like a couple extra
hours this week. So I would be looking
for that. That number didn't budge. And
then you look at average hourly
earnings. That number on a year over
year rate change ticked lower. So again
no real signs that this number is
creating enough jobs or creating the
right kind of jobs to sustain the
economy. Looks to me Jeff just you know
seasonal hiring maybe a little bit of
government fudging here but I I don't
think this is enough to really change
the narrative on the path that the
economy's headed.
>> Yeah I think the biggest red flag you
just mentioned it. Well there's a
there's a couple big red flags there but
the biggest red flag
leisure and hospitality. Okay let's
let's do numbers here. According to the
Bureau of Labor Statistics for the month
the establishment survey increased by
172,000.
Most economists were expecting a
deceleration to 85,000. Now they did
revise last month's
last month's figure higher so two months
in a row with plus 170,000 we haven't
seen something like that in well over a
year. Plus you get back to before that
you know 200,000. It's the best three
month stretch according to the payroll
numbers in well over a year. The problem
however is it doesn't fit with anything
else other than maybe the stock market
view of the economy which we know
doesn't really fit with anything. But in
the month of May, leisure and
hospitality hiring added 70,000 jobs,
which is the most in that sector, which
is already a dubious sector to begin
with. I mean, waiters and bartender
jobs, not the best, not the most robust
signal to begin with. But, leisure and
hospitality adding 70,000 jobs, the most
in over 3 years during a period when
energy costs have skyrocketed, when
people, consumers in particular, have
said, "We're going to start cutting back
on eating out. We're going to start
cutting back on our vacations. We're
going to start cutting back on all of
these things that go into leisure and
hospitality." Here we are to believe
that leisure and hospitality employers
said, "You know what? We need to
actually hire in a way we haven't in
years because we think things are going
to be robust." I mean, huge, huge red
flag right there. And of course, the
rest of the jobs in the private economy
came from the education and health care
sector, which is non-responsive to
economic terms to begin with. And then,
everything else beyond that was state
governments hiring for whatever reason.
I almost never do ads, and I say no to
the vast majority of those that are
brought to my attention, but I was
thrilled to be able to work with today's
video sponsor, Monetary Metals. And the
reason is because they're solving a big
problem, one that I've been highlighting
for a very long period of time. Gold is
a safe haven, but other than sitting in
a vault, it doesn't do anything.
Monetary Metals fixes that. They let you
earn real yield paid in physical gold
without giving up ownership. It's not a
fund, it's not a paper claim, it's your
gold working for you. Every month, more
gold gets deposited into your account.
It's simple, it's transparent, and it is
fully insured. If you believe in gold as
a long-term store of value as I do, this
changes everything. Go to
monetary-metals.com/snyder.
That's monetary-metals.com/snyder
for all the details. We absolutely thank
them for being the sponsor of today's
video, and now let's get back to it. So,
already several key big red flags in the
establishment survey, and that's even
before we get to all the rest of the
details, right, Steve?
>> Yeah, Jeff. You know, everybody knows
I'm in Orlando, you know, vacation
capital of the world. This is where tons
of part-time people over the summer get
jobs, and you know, there's some
interesting dynamics here because as we
head into the summer, Disney does
something that they they did last year,
which was anybody who makes a
reservation at Disney hotel gets a free
water park pass for their whole family
for that very first day of the
reservation. So, with that, you go from
one water park now to two, and of
course, everybody knows I'm a huge water
park efficient. I don't know if you're
ever looking for me, just go to one of
them. Their odds are I'm probably there.
But it's not the only parks. You see a
lot of this expansion of these part-time
jobs. But what's really interesting to
me, Jeff, isn't the fact that we saw the
staffing up because it's not unusual in
the summer we see businesses hoping that
business comes. If I staff up, maybe
people will come and consume. But what
I've noted so far this summer is
attendance levels at these parks have
been rather benign compared to what my
expectations were. And now as I look
around, I see other hotels around here
offering discounts and saying, "Hey, if
you can come in and spend money, or you
will give you past discounts." So, what
we're seeing here is businesses kind of
had no choice around, at least here, to
staff up a bit, and then they realized,
"Wait a minute, people don't have the
money."
>> Yeah, that's the big thing. That's what
the income data said. The the income
data showed unequivocally that there
wasn't nearly enough income. That was
going back to last fall, let alone
before we got to the energy price spike.
So, the income stat said the economy is
in big trouble to begin with, and then
all of a sudden, energy prices go up,
and leisure and hospitality businesses
say, "Now's the time to hire like we
haven't in years." It simply doesn't add
up. Now, it certainly doesn't add up in
relation to the other labor statistics
that came out from the household survey.
And over the last several years, the
household survey has time and again
proven to be not completely accurate,
not 100% precise, but certainly a better
job it does a better job of relaying the
picture of the labor market than the
establishment survey has, especially
before it gets to revisions in the
establishment survey. And the household
survey down three months in a row, and
down by a lot. Three months in a row, it
bounced in May up just a little bit less
than 150,000, which is nothing more than
a short-run fluctuation. But going back
to January, the household survey is down
a combined 300,000 positions. That's the
exact opposite of what we're seeing in
the establishment survey. So, if you're
forced to pick one or the other, and
let's be honest, you're you're being
forced to pick one or the other, you're
going to take the
you're going to take the household
survey every single time. And it just it
gets worse from there. So, not only
losing jobs since January, full-time
jobs, as I mentioned, down another
79,000. It was down 400,000
in April, which makes more sense when
you have businesses that are already
struggling from the previous economic
environment, suddenly energy costs rise
sharply. What are they going to do?
They're going to cut their labor costs.
They're going to say, "Look, I I love
you guys, you're our best employees, but
I have no choice. I've got to cut back
on my expenses. So, some of you are
going to be cut to part-time. Some of
you are going to I'm going to trim some
of your hours." So, full-time jobs over
the last couple months dropping by half
a million, that makes sense. Leisure and
hospitality jobs rising by 70,000 in
May, that makes absolutely no sense.
>> And your Jeff, there's some validation
here if we could look to the Challenger
Gray & Christmas stats, you know, the
planned layoffs. Of course, we see a ton
of tech jobs going.
And a lot of people might be struggling
with that, that wait a minute, you know,
here we're heading to earning seasons,
they're expected, you know, to put some
big numbers, and they almost have to put
up big numbers because the market's up.
Why would they be laying off if they're
getting maybe close to this AI
breakthrough? Well, simple. They realize
that they've got to hit these big
numbers to keep the market up. The only
answer is they've got to lay people off.
And that's one of the challenges that
every time you see profit margins or you
see earnings, you know, dip into a
negative position, if they stay there
too long, businesses are forced into
laying off because the alternative, they
go out of business. So, at this point,
you know, you look post pandemic, what
have we seen? Businesses have looked at
cut expenses every possible way. And
yet, every time they do, another bill
goes up. And now they're get They've
gotten to the point there just is no
alternative. We've got to continue to
cutting staff to maintain our profit
margins, to keep the market up. And I
think this is extremely important,
particularly as we're now getting close
to Q2 earnings. A lot of companies on
the hook now to hit some big numbers.
>> Yeah, so I mean, we look at the rest of
the establishment survey, you know, you
got the 70,000 leisure and hospitality.
All the rest of the industries,
they don't look terrible, but they look
a little bit closer to what you'd expect
given the economic climate that we're
dealing with. You know, retail trade,
wholesale, transportation, those were
all flat to slightly lower, which is,
you know, consistent at least with the
economic direction of the economic cycle
moving in the wrong in wrong way. But I
I want to come back to small businesses
because, Steve, you and I both know,
small businesses, they are, in many
ways, the engine of economic growth.
Yes, lots of people get work They work
for larger businesses, but in business
cycles, it all comes down to the smaller
midsize businesses. Are they adding
workers? Are they taking on risk? That's
where recovery really comes from. And on
the the other side of that, on the
recession, what happens with small
businesses see, you know, their their
revenues don't grow nearly as much as
they were expecting, their costs go up,
they stop hiring, and then they start
firing. And when small businesses start
firing, that's usually the sign the
cycle has really shifted. So, the NFIB
data just came out on Friday. What it
suggested, or at least the Bloomberg
write-up, I thought I liked the
Bloomberg write-up of it. Here, I'm
going to read it for you. The share of
US small businesses saying they're
planning new hires or having trouble
filling jobs fell in May to a six-year
low, according to the National
Federation of Independent Business. A
seasonally adjusted 9%, just 9% of
owners plan to create new jobs in the
next 3 months, down four percentage
points from April, which was already low
at 13%. So, almost no small business
owners are saying we're going to hire
we're going to add jobs over the next
couple months. And the share reporting
they had job openings they couldn't fill
fell by five percentage points to 29%.
That's what they said Both of those were
the lowest since May of 2020. Plus, the
proportion who cited labor costs
increased to the highest in the survey's
history, which means they are being
absolutely pressured by all sorts of
input costs, which means the last thing
they're going to be doing is robustly
hiring. I don't care if it's leisure and
hospitality or some other industry. They
are going to look at the current current
reality and say, "Look, there is no end
in sight to the energy picture. We know
gasoline prices and diesel prices are
going to be four, five dollars a gallon
for the foreseeable future, even if
everything goes right with the Iran
conflict. Energy prices are going to be
elevated for quite some time. At the
same time, we're not seeing a pick up in
business as Dollar Tree said, we're
seeing our customers cut back. We're
talking about Dollar Tree customers who
have to drive cutting back on buying
food at Dollar Tree, which tells you
they're are struggling badly. So, if
you're a small business owner, you see
your customers are hurting, you see your
costs start to really build up, it's
really pile up, you're not going to be
out there hiring a whole bunch of
workers. You're actually going to be
doing what the household survey
suggests, which is cutting back on
workers and cutting back on hours and
income.
>> Yeah, because the next step here, Jeff,
is that we see sales start to drop. So,
we go back to October, we see incomes
are starting to roll over. In January,
we see personal disposable income goes
negative. And what is the next shock
that hits? It's you know, retail sales
has somewhat been immune to a lot of
this. Somehow they just held up, at
least on a nominal basis. But as you
follow, you know, disposable incomes,
it's going to drop off a cliff. And I
think this is what business owners are
starting to see. I mean, you know, we
can go back to Home Depot and Lowe's and
they said, "Wow, the first 3 months of
the year everything looked good." And
then in April, all of a sudden,
everything dropped off and went
negative. And we're starting to hear,
you know, companies like Ford saying,
"Yeah, all of a sudden sales dropped off
in May." So, all of a sudden, out of
nowhere, businesses thought everything
was going to be okay, that consumers
were going to be able to afford higher
prices, that they were going to be able
to pass them on, and that, you know, as
soon as these tax refund checks started
to dry up, what happens? Sales plunging,
plunging, plunging. And next thing you
know, the big drop hasn't happened yet.
But I think the small business owners
are kind of waking up to reality of,
this is as good as it's going to get,
and there's no reason for us to hire,
because we're not going to have any
demand because our customers are going
broke.
>> Yeah, that's the other thing, too,
Steve, right? I mean, we talked about
this before. In fact, it's one of the
one of the things you keep focusing on,
tax refunds.
Um Five Below, one of the competitors to
Dollar Tree. Five Below came out this
past week and said, "You know what? It
really looks like the tax refund stuff,
it cushioned the initial energy shock
blow from our customers, you know, the
lower income consumers who shop
regularly at dollar stores." Though, as
we've been saying and we've been
documenting, uh dollar stores have seen
somewhat of a boom, a pick up in
business from higher income Americans,
but
the dollar store, that you know, Five
Below said, "It looks like it really
looks like we could tell, almost to the
week, which week the tax refund money
went out." And then Walmart came out and
said the same thing. They said, "We see
that the tax refund money is running
out, which is a shift in our business,
which has us concerned about what the
what the coming quarters look like." So,
there has been that cushion, uh as you
said, Steve, that it seemed like retail
sales and spending overall. Now, if you
look at the personal consumption
expenditures that go along with the
income data that we just cited, it did
soften, but nowhere near as much as
income
income did. So, what you can see is that
incomes are dragging down and down and
down and and spending is coming along
lagging behind being pulled lower and
lower and lower, but it hasn't been
pulled all the way to where incomes are.
And so, what all these retailers are
saying is that we're starting to see
around the margins and the edges with
the tax refund money gone, with the
energy shock as bad as it is, that sort
of financial gravity or economic gravity
is beginning to pull on consumers, which
means eventually, probably in the short
run, spending is going to go down, too.
Which just means the labor market is the
is the next shoe to drop, right, Steve?
>> Yeah, absolutely. Because you know, we
look at energy shocks, we've talked
about the timeline before, and we're
starting to see Jeff, you know, these
real effects now that hey, it was
propped up by these tax refund checks,
and now all of a sudden they're drying
up, and gasoline prices haven't dropped.
And then you start thinking about the
summer season. Of course you've got, you
know, utility bills because the summer's
going to be hot, you're going to run
your AC. So, you've got to make cuts in
other places. Vacations, obviously one
of those. Airline travel, driving,
everything's going to start to shift
now. And the problem is it literally
looks like to me, you know, that we are
now past the point of total no return,
that even if gas prices got cut, you
know, by 50% tomorrow, I think for the
average consumer now it's way too late.
Businesses are not going to see that
anything is hopeful here, because
they've been looking at the stock market
saying, "Okay, it's been going up." And
usually that's a great barometer to get
people to come out and spend, but this
just isn't driving it enough. So again,
you guys you just said, the big next
shoe to drop is retail sales, then labor
market, and then it's game over.
>> Yeah, we talked about this last week,
too, I think, you know, the CEO survey
from the Conference Board. And it's, of
course, it doesn't line up with the
establishment survey at all. Again, you
have to realize the establishment
survey, even if you take it at face
value, it is very narrowly construed.
It's just leisure and hospitality, just
education and healthcare, and just state
governments. Everything else outside of
that is either zero or negative. That
fits with the data, including the CEO
survey. We talked about this last week,
you know, uh the Conference Board
measure of CEO confidence had dropped to
47 from 59. And CEOs reported that the
economy, according to them, was
materially worse than it had been 6
months ago, and they expected conditions
to weaken even more over the next 6
months, which is an ominous sign when
you put that together with the NFIB
data. So, you've got corporate CEOs, the
big company saying, "We don't like the
way things have gone the last couple
months, and we don't see it getting any
better the next 6 months." You've got
small business owners who are saying,
"We don't like the way things are going.
Our costs are up. Our margins are thin
to begin with. Now, we don't even care
if we can't afford workers because we're
not going to hire them anyway. And by
the way, our outlook is even darker than
it is for CEOs." So, big businesses,
small businesses, they look like the
household survey, not the establishment.
In fact, they look like the income data,
not the establishment survey. So, once
again, we're back to the same problem we
have before. The payroll number comes
out, it beats expectations to a huge
degree. Everybody goes it runs around
saying, "Oh my god, the labor market's
going to be strong and robust. The Fed's
going to have to hike rates here." And
then a couple months later, all of that
euphoria and and enthusiasm just
disappears because it was never real to
begin with. And this report has even
more red flags than all the rest of them
that we've seen.
>> Yeah, Jeff, and then we pull this all
together with what's going on with
private credit, and people wondering,
like, why are funds yo-gating
redemptions? Is this because it's all
tied to this the consumer? You know, if
incomes are dropping, and spending's
dropping, well, that means inventories
aren't moving, receivables, payables,
none of this stuff is going to happen.
And next thing, you've got all this
money tied up in it. The problem is, of
course, you've got to gate investors
because the reality is a lot of these
funds, they know that if the economy
continues to weaken, they're not the
ones that are going to take a hit. It's
all the shareholders. They need to make
sure they're all locked in and gated
because somebody's going to eat these
losses, and it's going to be them. And
that's exactly the problems we see, you
know, with every energy crisis. At
first, uh there's hope that we can get
through this, that we can handle it. And
then next thing you know, you hit that
tipping point, and it all starts to fall
apart. Now we're starting to see it, and
everybody's holding on hoping something
changes. The only question is, is it too
late?
>> Yeah, that's private credit is a is
great way to end this because it is
it's depending upon the labor market
both as what it's going to do to
consumers and therefore consumers and
and consumer lending, but also as a
signal about the state of its bread and
butter marketplace. Remember what
private credit was built on. It was
built on exactly the businesses we just
went over in the NFIB survey. If they're
struggling over their input costs and
their their what they see as their
revenue potential, they have no money
left to pay their loans. And what's the
easiest thing to do? You don't want to
do it, but what's the easiest thing to
do? You're a small business owner,
you're facing some pretty dire
circumstances. Your energy bills are
going up. You don't really have enough
work, or at least you don't think you're
going to have enough work for your
workers.
First thing you do is cut back on
workers, but the other thing that you
can do really easy is just to not pay
your loan. I'm just going to I'm going
to set it aside for a couple months, and
I'll come back to it when everything
picks up again, and everything will be
fine. You start to see struggling
businesses start to fall further and
further behind on their debt. And when
that happens, it has this this chilling
effect all across the system. And of
course, that's exactly what investors
are worried about, why they're keep
pulling their money out of these private
credit funds. They see this business
cycle develop, they see the energy shock
on top, they presumably see the
establishment survey and laugh at that
and set that aside, and they see the
household survey and say, "Yeah, that
makes a lot more sense." And so they're
running for the exits because they can
see where all of these points intersect.
And they intersect not in, you know, a
robust inflationary environment where
the Fed has to hike rates to cool off
the economy and to calm down in consumer
prices. All these lines intersect in
exactly the same way they always do,
which is the energy shock recession.